<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mores on Eric Ngigi</title>
    <link>https://ericngigi.com/more/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mores on Eric Ngigi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ericngigi.com/more/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing the Journey of a Software Engineer</title>
      <link>https://ericngigi.com/more/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericngigi.com/more/portfolio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-journey-with-alx-africa&#34;&gt;My Journey with ALX Africa&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since joining ALX Africa, my journey has been filled with learning, growth, and exciting challenges. I&amp;rsquo;ve had the opportunity to work on various projects, collaborate with talented peers, and expand my skills as a software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;month-2-week-10-group-work-slide-deck&#34;&gt;Month 2 Week 10 Group Work: Slide Deck&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project-regional-integration-through-a-marketplace-application&#34;&gt;Project: Regional Integration Through A Marketplace Application.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Month 2 Week 10, our group collaborated on a project that pushed our boundaries and showcased our ability to work together as a team. Here&amp;rsquo;s a brief overview of our project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define clear project objectives and goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribute tasks among team members based on expertise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a functional prototype that demonstrates key features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;challenges&#34;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overcoming technical hurdles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective communication within the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meeting deadlines while ensuring code quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;achievements&#34;&gt;Achievements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successful implementation of [Feature 1].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seamless integration of [Feature 2].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positive feedback from mentors during review sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slide-deck-highlights&#34;&gt;Slide Deck Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our slide deck for the Month 2 Week 10 project presentation encapsulated the essence of our collaborative effort. It included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt; An overview of the project&amp;rsquo;s purpose and significance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Members:&lt;/strong&gt; Brief introductions to each team member and their roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Objectives:&lt;/strong&gt; Clear outline of the goals we aimed to achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Details:&lt;/strong&gt; Insights into the technologies and tools used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges &amp;amp; Solutions:&lt;/strong&gt; How we tackled obstacles and found innovative solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features Showcase:&lt;/strong&gt; Demonstrations of key features with screenshots and code snippets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achievements:&lt;/strong&gt; Highlights of our accomplishments and milestones reached.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future Scope:&lt;/strong&gt; Potential avenues for project expansion and improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments:&lt;/strong&gt; Gratitude to mentors, peers, and ALX Africa for their support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can view the group slides by clicking on the link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1taYlugA4cp6gsFfGEdspJpLBJJDN4r_igYWR7sI1KKQ/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Google Sheets Slide&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-youtube-video&#34;&gt;Group YouTube Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;team-maven-showcase-video&#34;&gt;Team Maven Showcase Video&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recorded a comprehensive YouTube video to visually present our project&amp;rsquo;s outcomes and functionalities. In this video, we cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live demos of the project in action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insights into our problem-solving strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team dynamics and collaboration process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A walkthrough of key code snippets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflections on the overall learning experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the video and explore the tangible results of our hard work and dedication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y4mvNF_Z6JA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journey at ALX Africa has been transformative, and the Month 2 Week 10 project was a testament to my growth as a software engineer. I look forward to embracing more challenges and learning opportunities as I continue to evolve in this dynamic field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://ericngigi.com/more/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericngigi.com/more/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a passionate Linux enthusiast and free software advocate with years of experience in developing and maintaining Linux systems. I have a deep understanding of the inner workings of the Linux kernel and have extensive knowledge of various Linux distributions, including Arch Linux, Debian, Ubuntu, and CentOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also skilled in various programming languages, including Python, Go, JAMstack and Bash scripting, and have used these languages to automate and streamline various processes in my DevOps career. My expertise in automation and infrastructure as code has allowed me to optimize system performance, reduce downtime, and increase scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a free software advocate, I firmly believe in the importance of open-source software and its ability to empower individuals and organizations to achieve their goals. I am committed to sharing my knowledge and promoting free software whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a Linux expert who is passionate about free software and has the technical skills to make a real difference in your organization, then look no further. Let&amp;rsquo;s work together to build the perfect solution for your needs. You can find more detailed information about my professional experience in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/erik-ngigi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;LinkedIn profile&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is mostly about my software development/DevOps adventures. You can find here various how-tos, tutorials, and
write-ups about my personal project experiences. In case you need to contact me, please email
at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ericmosesngigi@gmail.com&#34; &gt;ericmosesngigi@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the Link to download my &lt;a href=&#34;https://ericngigi.com/more/Curriculum-Vitae.pdf&#34; &gt;resume&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the link to download my &lt;a href=&#34;https://ericngigi.com/more/Cover-Letter.pdf&#34; &gt;cover letter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
